<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc category="std" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-thomson-httpbis-deprecate-http-latest" updates="2616">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Deprecating http:">
      Deprecating the 'http:' URI Scheme
    </title>

    <author initials="M." surname="Thomson" fullname="Martin Thomson">
      <organization>Microsoft</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>-</street>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>martin.thomson@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2013"/>
    <area>APPS</area>
    <workgroup>HTTPBIS</workgroup>
    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
    <keyword>http</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>
        The http: URI scheme has proven to be problematic.  This document deprecates its use.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>
        Anyone who uses <xref target="RFC2616">HTTP</xref> without <xref target="RFC5246">TLS</xref>
        (i.e., <xref target="RFC2818">HTTPS</xref>) runs a very real risk of being pwned.
      </t>

      <t>
        This document attempts to remedy this by making the <spanx style="verb">http:</spanx>
        scheme historic.
      </t>

      <section anchor="terminology" title="Conventions and Terminology">
        <t>
          In cases where normative language needs to be emphasized, this document falls back on
          established shorthands for expressing interoperability requirements on implementations:
          the capitalized words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "SHOULD" and "MAY".  The meaning of these is
          described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="MUST NOT use http:">
      <t>
        HTTP clients and servers MUST NOT use <spanx style="verb">http:</spanx> resources.
      </t>
    </section>
    
    <section title="Why Not Opportunistically Encrypt?">
      <t>
        Opportunistic encryption is fine if your adversary isn't on-path.  It's pretty ineffectual
        if your adversary is able to interspose themselves somehow.  There is now evidence to
        suggest that interception capabilities are less difficult to achieve than originally
        thought.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Why Not Trust on First Use?">
      <t>
        TOFU is unsatisfactory.  Because it is effectively a pin for the lifetime of a certificate,
        it has several issues:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
            Key rollover cannot occur without exposure to an active attack, or some form of
            succession plan.  The typical key pinning succession plan involves providing alternative
            pins under the protection of a trusted certificate.  This sort of plan cannot be enacted
            without a lead time equal to the pin duration.  The successor key has to be available
            for this entire period.
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            From an operational perspective, this is difficult.  In order to ensure that the risk of
            exposure or exfiltration of the private key for the successor, the private key for the
            successor needs to be backed up.  Any service that is unwilling to obtain third-party
            validation of their certificates seems unlikely to be inclined to perform this step.
          </t>
          <t>
            Pinning makes it difficult to scale out services without sharing of private keys.
            Clients will reject connections that offer private keys other than the one they first
            see.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Why Not Externalize the Consequences?">
      <t>
        That's what we've been doing for years.  That turned out to be a political nightmare once
        people found out.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>
        The IETF has partnered with several large organizations to perform enforcement.  Users of
        <spanx style="verb">http:</spanx> URIs will be pwned.  Operators of sites that offer <spanx
        style="verb">http:</spanx> resources will be pwned.
      </t>
    </section>
<!--
    <section anchor="ack" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>
      </t>
    </section>
-->
  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2616.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2818.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5246.xml"?>
    </references>
   <!-- <references title="Informative References">
    </references>-->

    <!--
        <section title="Change Log">
        <t>[[The RFC Editor is requested to remove this section at publication.]]</t>
        <t>Changes since -0-1:
        <list style="symbols">
        <t>Document created.</t>
        </list>
        </t>
        </section>
    -->
  </back>
</rfc>
