<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc category="std" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-ietf-rtcweb-alpn-latest">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="ALPN for WebRTC">
      Application Layer Protocol Negotiation for Web Real-Time Communications (WebRTC)
    </title>

    <author initials="M." surname="Thomson" fullname="Martin Thomson">
      <organization>Mozilla</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>331 E Evelyn Street</street>
          <city>Mountain View</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>94041</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <email>martin.thomson@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2016"/>
    <area>RAI</area>
    <workgroup>RTCWEB</workgroup>
    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
    <keyword>ALPN</keyword>
    <keyword>Protocol</keyword>
    <keyword>Identifier</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>
        Application Layer Protocol Negotiation (ALPN) labels are defined for use in identifying Web
        Real-Time Communications (WebRTC) usages of Datagram Transport Layer Security (DTLS).
        Labels are provided for identifying a session that uses a combination of WebRTC compatible
        media and data, and for identifying a session requiring confidentiality protection from web
        applications.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>

    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>
        <xref target="I-D.ietf-rtcweb-overview">Web Real-Time Communications (WebRTC)</xref> uses
        <xref target="RFC6347">Datagram Transport Layer Security (DTLS)</xref> to secure all
        peer-to-peer communications.
      </t>
      <t>
        Identifying WebRTC protocol usage with <xref target="RFC7301">Application Layer Protocol
        Negotiation (ALPN)</xref> enables an endpoint to positively identify WebRTC uses and
        distinguish them from other DTLS uses.
      </t>
      <t>
        Different WebRTC uses can be advertised and behavior can be constrained to what is
        appropriate to a given use.  In particular, this allows for the identifications of sessions
        that require confidentiality protection from the application that manages the signaling for
        the session.
      </t>

      <section title="Conventions and Terminology" anchor="terminology">
       <t>
         At times, this document falls back on shorthands for establishing interoperability
         requirements on implementations: the capitalized words "MUST", "SHOULD" and "MAY".  These
         terms are defined in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
       </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="ALPN Labels for WebRTC">
      <t>
        The following identifiers are defined for use in ALPN:
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="webrtc:">
            The DTLS session is used to establish keys for a Secure Real-time Transport Protocol
            (SRTP) - known as DTLS-SRTP - as described in <xref target="RFC5764"/>.  The DTLS record
            layer is used for <xref target="I-D.ietf-rtcweb-data-channel">WebRTC data
            channels</xref>.
          </t>
          <t hangText="c-webrtc:">
            The DTLS session is used for confidential WebRTC communications, where peers agree to
            maintain the confidentiality of the media, as described in <xref
            target="confidentiality"/>.  However, data provided over data channels do not receive
            the same level of confidentiality protection.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        Both identifiers describe the same basic protocol: a DTLS session that is used to provide
        keys for an SRTP session in combination with WebRTC data channels.  Either SRTP or data
        channels could be absent.  The data channels send <xref target="RFC4960">Stream Control
        Transmission Protocol (SCTP)</xref> over the DTLS record layer, which can be multiplexed
        with SRTP on the same UDP flow.  WebRTC requires the use of <xref
        target="RFC5245">Interactive Communication Establishment (ICE)</xref> to establish the UDP
        flow, but this is not covered by the identifier.
      </t>
      <t>
        A more thorough definition of what WebRTC communications entail is included in <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-rtcweb-transports"/>.
      </t>
      <t>
        There is no functional difference between the identifiers except that an endpoint
        negotiating <spanx style="verb">c-webrtc</spanx> makes a promise to preserve the
        confidentiality of the media it receives.
      </t>
      <t>
        A peer that is not aware of whether it needs to request confidentiality can use either form.
        A peer in the client role MUST offer both identifiers if it is not aware of a need for
        confidentiality. A peer in the server role SHOULD select <spanx style="verb">webrtc</spanx>
        if it does not need confidentiality protection.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Media Confidentiality" anchor="confidentiality">
      <t>
        Private communications in WebRTC depend on separating control (i.e., signaling) capabilities
        and access to media <xref target="I-D.ietf-rtcweb-security-arch"/>.  In this way, an
        application can establish a session that is end-to-end confidential, where the ends in
        question are user agents (or browsers) and not the signaling application.  This allows an
        application to manage signaling for a session, without having access to the media that is
        exchanged in the session.
      </t>
      <t>
        Without some form of indication that is securely bound to the session, a WebRTC endpoint is
        unable to properly distinguish between session that requires this confidentiality protection
        and one that does not.  The ALPN identifier provides that signal.
      </t>
      <t>
        A browser is required to enforce this confidentiality protection using isolation controls
        similar to those used in content cross-origin protections (see <eref
        target="http://www.w3.org/TR/2012/CR-html5-20121217/browsers.html#origin">Section 5.3</eref>
        of <xref target="HTML5"/>).  These protections ensure that media is protected from
        applications.  Applications are not able to read or modify the contents of a protected flow
        of media.  Media that is produced from a session using the <spanx
        style="verb">c-webrtc</spanx> identifier MUST only be displayed to users.
      </t>
      <t>
        These confidentiality protections do not apply to data that is sent using data channels.
        Confidential data depends on having both data sources and consumers that are exclusively
        browser- or user-based.  No mechanisms currently exist to take advantage of data
        confidentiality, though some use cases suggest that this could be useful, for example,
        confidential peer-to-peer file transfer.  Alternative labels might be provided in future to
        support these use cases.
      </t>
      <t>
        Generally speaking, ensuring confidentiality depends on authenticating the communications
        peer.  This mechanism explicitly does not define a specific authentication method; a WebRTC
        endpoint that accepts a session with this ALPN identifier MUST respect confidentiality no
        matter what identity is attributed to a peer.
      </t>
      <t>
        RTP middleboxes and entities that forward media or data cannot promise to maintain
        confidentiality.  Any entity that forwards content, or records content for later access by
        entities other than the authenticated peer, MUST NOT offer or accept a session with the
        <spanx style="verb">c-webrtc</spanx> identifier.
      </t>
   </section>

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>
        Confidential communications depends on more than just an agreement from browsers.
      </t>
      <t>
        Information is not confidential if it is displayed to those other than to whom it is
        intended.  <xref target="I-D.ietf-rtcweb-security-arch">Peer authentication</xref> is
        necessary to ensure that data is only sent to the intended peer.
      </t>
      <t>
        This is not a digital rights management mechanism.  Even with an authenticated peer, a user
        is not prevented from using other mechanisms to record or forward media.  This means that
        (for example) screen recording devices, tape recorders, portable cameras, or a cunning
        arrangement of mirrors could variously be used to record or redistribute media once
        delivered.  Similarly, if media is visible or audible (or otherwise accessible) to others in
        the vicinity, there are no technical measures that protect the confidentiality of that
        media.
      </t>
      <t>
        The only guarantee provided by this mechanism and the browser that implements it is that the
        media was delivered to the user that was authenticated.  Individual users will still need to
        make a judgment about how their peer intends to respect the confidentiality of any
        information provided.
      </t>
      <t>
        On a shared computing platform like a browser, other entities with access to that platform
        (i.e., web applications), might be able to access information that would compromise the
        confidentiality of communications.  Implementations MAY choose to limit concurrent access to
        input devices during confidential communications sessions.
      </t>
      <t>
        For instance, another application that is able to access a microphone might be able to
        sample confidential audio that is playing through speakers.  This is true even if acoustic
        echo cancellation, which attempts to prevent this from happening, is used.  Similarly, an
        application with access to a video camera might be able to use reflections to obtain all or
        part of a confidential video stream.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>
        The following two entries are added to the "Application Layer Protocol Negotiation (ALPN)
        Protocol IDs" registry established by <xref target="RFC7301"/>:
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="webrtc:">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            The <spanx style="verb">webrtc</spanx> label identifies mixed media and data
            communications using SRTP and data channels:
            <list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="Protocol:">WebRTC Media and Data</t>
              <t hangText="Identification Sequence:">0x77 0x65 0x62 0x72 0x74 0x63 ("webrtc")</t>
              <t hangText="Specification:">This document (RFCXXXX)</t>
            </list>
          </t>
          <t hangText="c-webrtc:">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            The <spanx style="verb">c-webrtc</spanx> label identifies confidential WebRTC
            communications:
            <list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="Protocol:">Confidential WebRTC Media and Data</t>
              <t hangText="Identification Sequence:">0x63 0x2d 0x77 0x65 0x62 0x72 0x74 0x63
              ("c-webrtc")</t>
              <t hangText="Specification:">This document (RFCXXXX)</t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <!--
        <appendix title="Change Log">
        <t>[[The RFC Editor is requested to remove this section at publication.]]</t>
        <t>Changes since -0-1:
        <list style="symbols">
        <t>Document created.</t>
        </list>
        </t>
        </appendix>
    -->
  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6347.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5764.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7301.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-rtcweb-data-channel.xml"?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4960.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5245.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-rtcweb-overview.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-rtcweb-security-arch.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-rtcweb-transports.xml"?>
      <reference anchor="HTML5" target="http://www.w3.org/TR/2012/CR-html5-20121217/">
        <front>
          <title>
            HTML 5
          </title>
          <author initials="R." surname="Berjon" fullname="Robin Berjon"/>
          <author initials="T." surname="Leithead" fullname="Travis Leithead"/>
          <author initials="E." surname="Doyle Navara" fullname="Erika Doyle Navara"/>
          <author initials="E." surname="O'Connor" fullname="Edward O'Connor"/>
          <author initials="S." surname="Pfeiffer" fullname="Silvia Pfeiffer"/>
          <date year="2010" month="August"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="CR" value="CR-html5-20121217"/>
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
